<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christs glorious appearance to judgement in two choice sermons ... / Mr. Samuel Malbon.</title>
            <author>Malbon, Samuel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51626</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M311</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10883</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13115131</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13115131</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97739</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51626)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97739)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 427:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christs glorious appearance to judgement in two choice sermons ... / Mr. Samuel Malbon.</title>
                  <author>Malbon, Samuel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Hancock, Sen. and Jun. ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisements: p. 46.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Second Advent --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Judgment Day --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97739:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97739:1"/>
            <p>CHRISTS GLORIOUS APPEARANCE TO Judgement.</p>
            <p>IN Two Choice SERMONS OF THAT <hi>Reverend Miniſter of Chriſt</hi> Mr. SAMUEL MALBON.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>John Hancock Sen.</hi> and <hi>Jun.</hi> at the Three Bibles in <hi>Popes-Head-Alley</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermons">
            <pb facs="tcp:97739:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97739:2"/>
            <head>THE SUMME OF TWO SERMONS Preached <hi>Aug.</hi> 19—</head>
            <div n="1" type="sermon">
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>MAT. XVI. 27.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <q>For the Son of Man ſhall come in the Glory of his Father, with his Angels: and then he ſhall render toward every Man accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his works.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THIS verſe hath either reference to the immediate foregoing, or rather to the 24. as a further Argument to preſs that difficult duty. For the Son of Man, <hi>(i.e.)</hi> the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who is both God and Man, as God the Son and only begotten of God, as Man the Son of Man, born of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> though not begotten by man as other men are. The Son of Man Chriſt Jeſus in his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature ſhall come. We read of a double
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97739:3"/>coming of Chriſt; The firſt is paſt long ago, when he was born into the world, then Chriſt came to obey the Law, and by ſuffering to ſatisfie Juſtice, and ſo to ſave ſinners; All thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the ſinful ſons of <hi>Adam,</hi> who were from all Eternity elected, and ſhould in time be effectually called, and believe on him. The ſecond coming of Chriſt is yet to be, <hi>The Son of Man ſhall come;</hi> which was not only true when it was ſpoken by Chriſt, but alſo ſtill is true; of which coming of Chriſt we reade, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.10, 11. This coming of Chriſt it will be to Judgement at the end of the world, at the Reſurrection, then Ieſus Chriſt ſhall come to judge the world; of this coming of Chriſt my Text ſpeaks, as appears by the laſt words, <hi>And then ſhall he, &amp;c.</hi> which coming of Chriſt was long ago foretold and propheſied in <hi>Jude</hi> 14.14, <hi>&amp;c. in the Glory of his Father;</hi> this Chriſt mentions, that we might not think his ſecond coming will be like his firſt; then he came under the habit and ſhape of a ſervant; then he came to ſuffer, to be judg'd and condemn'd by men, and therefore came in a mean and deſpiſed way; but when he ſhall come again the ſecond time, he will come as a Iudge to be a Iudge: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will come in the glory, &amp;c. He will come like himſelf with his Angels, with all the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels accompanying him, who are his. And then, and not till then, he ſhall, Ieſus Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97739:3"/>ſhall reward, or render to every man, one and another, good and bad, high, low, &amp;c. accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their works; not according to their thoughts and words of themſelves, not accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their wills and wiſhes, not according to their meanings and purpoſes, &amp;c. but according to their works; not according to the works of others, but according to their own works.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Obſervations.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. There is to be a day of Iudgement. 2. Jeſus Chriſt the Son of Man is to be the Judge at this day. 3. When Chriſt ſhall come to judge the world, he ſhall come in the Glory of his Father. 4. With the Angels. 5. The Angels are Chriſts, with his Angels. 6. That at the day of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment every man ſhall receive a reward from Chriſt according to his works.</p>
                  <p>D. 2 <hi>That Jeſus Chriſt the Son of Man is to be the Judge at the day of Judgement.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That Ieſus Chriſt who ſuffered upon the Croſs at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> he ſhall be the Iudge at this day; and that in that nature in which he ſuffered God gave the Law by a Man, <hi>viz. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;</hi> and he will judge men according to the Law, by the Son of Man, Ieſus Chriſt, who was typified by <hi>Moſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>John</hi> 12.47. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.17. Theſe places ſpeak no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing againſt my Text; but the meaning of them is this, either thus, That the firſt and chief End of his coming was not to judge the world, but to ſave it,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97739:4"/>or rather thoſe places are ſpoken on concerning his firſt coming, That then he came not to judge, &amp;c. The truth of this doctrine appears by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places of Scripture; the day of Iudgement is not often ſpoken of, but this is hinted, That Ieſus Chriſt ſhall be the Iudge, <hi>Iob</hi> 19.26. that is, judge the world, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.38, 39, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Hence 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. its called, <hi>The Iudgement-Seat of Chriſt;</hi> and very often called, <hi>The Day of Chriſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.8. Phil. 1.6. and 10, &amp;c. Acts 17.31. Rom. 2.16. <hi>Christ ſhall judge the world<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> not that the Father and Spirit are excluded, but becauſe Chriſt in his humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture will appear, will ſpeak and paſs the Sentence; and he ſpeaking, God will ſpeak by him; and he judging God will judge by him and therefore its ſaid in that <hi>Acts</hi> 17.31. <hi>He hath appointed a day in which he will judge the World by that Man whom he hath appointed.</hi> The Iudgment will be of the whole Trinity, as to the Conſent and Authority; but it will be Chriſts as to the viſible Acts, Promulgation and Execution of the Sentence; as when Iudges among men condemn Malefactors, it is by the Authority of the Prince, though the trial and ſentence be actually by him. Some obſerve there are four things to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in Iudgment, 1. Judicial Power. 2 The internal Approbation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f good, and deteſtation of evil. 3. The Retribution of Reward; Theſe three agree to each Perſon in the Trinity; But
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97739:4"/>then 4. There is an external ſitting upon the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal, and pronouncing of ſentence, and in this reſpect the Father judgeth no man, but hath committed all Iudgement to the Son, <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.23. This is part of Chriſt his Kingly Office, as he is the Fathers <hi>Prorex</hi> and rules for him; Chriſt hath three Offices, Prieſt, Prophet and King; as he is a Prieſt, ſo he died to ſave his people, and ever lives to make interceſſion for them; as he is a Prophet, ſo he reveals the minde of his Father to them; as he is a King, ſo he now rules the world, and will hereafter judge it; Chriſts Kingly Office will not end till the day of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be paſt, and then he ſhall give up the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to his Father, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24.</p>
                  <p>This is an honour fit for none elſe but God and Chriſt to be the great Judge of the whole world. All men ſhall be judged at this day, except Chriſt only, who ſhall be the Judge. Chriſt ſhall be the Judge, not that he hath taken this work upon himſelf, but the Father hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed him to it, (as before) God appointed Chriſt, and ſent him at his firſt coming to ſave the world; and he hath appointed him, and will ſend him at his ſecond coming to judge the world. That there ſhall be a day of Iudgement, even Reaſon it ſelf manifeſteth; and therefore the Heathen themſelves had an apprehenſion of ſome ſuch time; but Ieſus Chriſt ſhall be the Iudge, that is a Truth only made known by the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97739:5"/>Scripture, and therefore wholly to be receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by faith; but though the truth could not have bin known by reaſon, yet its no way contrary to it; yea, there may be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral reaſons given why it ſhould be ſo, which I ſhall but touch.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The firſt reaſon may be taken from his firſt coming; he was much abaſed at his firſt coming, therefore he ſhall come again and be exalted; he was arraign'd, accuſed and condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by men at his firſt coming, therefore he ſhall be the Iudge of men at his ſecond coming, <hi>Phil,</hi> 2.8, 9, 10. which is to be at the day of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.9, 10, 11. This is an ordinary Piece of Gods Providence towards his people, the ſame evil he caſts them into now, he exalts them into the contrary good in his time; as the Lord had a purpoſe to make <hi>Joſeph</hi> Ruler over all <hi>Egypt;</hi> but firſt he makes him a ſlave: ſo God had a meaning to make Chriſt Iudge of men, and therefore firſt ſuffers him to be judged by men, This may be one reaſon to prove, that Chriſt ſhall be the Iudge at this day, and it hath not a little in it to prove the day of Judgment it ſelf: The ſufferings of Gods people in the world prove that, much more doth the ill uſage and ſufferings of Chriſt prove it, that there will be a time when the innocency of Chriſt ſhall be cleared before all the world, and his enemies fully puniſh'd, which that it might be indeed,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97739:5"/>God hath appointed Chriſt Judge at this day, <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.22, 23. Chriſt ſhall be the Judge, that he might be honoured before and by all the world, and there's reaſon for it; becauſe he was diſhonour'd and diſgrac'd in and by the world; Chriſt ſhall judge the world, that it may appear to all men how the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther honours him and loves him; and what a difference there is betwixt Chriſt and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men</p>
                  <p n="2">2. This will be for the Honour of God, his Greatneſs and Sovereignty; to judge the world by another: Kings on earth ſeldom judge any themſelves, but execute Judgement by others Hereby the Iuſtice of God alſo will appear the more, in that he will judge men by Man, by one who was fleſh and blood like themſelves, <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.27.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Chriſt is the Saviour of the world, of all thoſe who do and will believe on him; he is the way of ſalvation to his People, they are ſaved by him; and for others, thoſe who live (be ſure) where the Goſpel is preacht, the great reaſon of their deſtruction and perdition will be, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they do not and will not believe on him, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.19 this may be another reaſon, becauſe its by believing on him that thoſe (who ſhall have it) come to have a right to eternal life: they ſhall have it for his ſake; and therefore from him,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97739:6"/>and its for not believing on him that others will ſuffer eternal death, and chiefly deſerve it, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it ſhall be inflicted by him; and in this the juſtice of God will appear alſo the more in the deſtruction of unbelievers, in that he will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn them by him, whom he offered to them to be their Saviour; hereby wicked mens mouths will be ſtopt indeed, they will have nothing to ſay.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, Chriſt now rules and governs the world. <hi>Mat. laſt.</hi> 18. the world is Chriſt's, as by Gods Gift, ſo by his Purchaſe; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, <hi>Christ ſhall be, &amp;c.</hi> that ſo wicked men might ſee their Judge, God being inviſible, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.30.</p>
                  <p>Sixthly, Chriſt hath liv'd in the world amongſt men, and ſo by experience he knows their tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations and ways, therefore the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Chriſt is fit to be an High Prieſt,</hi> Heb. 4.15. and therefore he may be ſaid to be fit to be Mans Judge; he knows what it is to live in the world; Chriſt will be able to anſwer any thing that wicked men may plead, that they liv'd in a ſinful world, and that they had ſuch and ſuch tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations, &amp;c. in that he hath lived in the world, and bin tempted as much and more then any.</p>
                  <p>USE I. <hi>Inſtruct.</hi> 1. <hi>Learn hence willingly to ſuffer and undergo any thing for God you will be no loſers in the end; the lower you are brought for God, the higher he will exalt you one day;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97739:6"/>the more diſgrac't for God, the more will he ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour you; the more you do for God, the more he will own you hereafter; this we may learn by Gods dealings with Chriſt, none brought lower then Chriſt, and therefore none ſhall be exalted higher, none diſgrac't more, and therefore God will honour none ſo much; none ever did ſo much for God, and therefore none ſhall ever be own<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d ſo much by God: Chriſt loſt nothing by any thing he did, ſuffered or underwent for God, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly, learn not to judge of men as they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear outwardly to you in this life; who more mean, poor, and every way low while in the world then Chriſt; yet he, even he, that poor (but bleſſed) Ieſus Chriſt who had not a ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſe to put his head in while in the world, ſhall be the Judge of the whole world; It will not be with men hereafter according to their condition while here; who would have thought ſeeing Jeſus Chriſt here on earth, when born in the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ble, lying in the Marger; when buffered and ſpit on, when hanging upon the Croſs, &amp;c. who would and could have thought; who did think of thoſe who ſaw him, (without an Eye of faith) that he ſhould have bin the Judge of the world at this great day</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly, is it ſo, then what awful, honourable and reverent althoughts ſhould we have of Jeſus Christ; how ſhould we fear and everence him in our hearts; Judges on earth are feared, reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97739:7"/>honour'd and fear'd, how much more ſhould Jeſus Chriſt the Judge of the whole world? Chriſt was a man as we are, (ſin only excepted) but he was and is God as well as man; and though a man, yet you hear he is to be the Judge of all men; he is to be a Judge of Iudges them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (to whom, but that there are none ſuch here) a word might have been spoken particularly as ſuch, from this doctrine, to put them in minde, that as they are Iudges of others, ſo they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſhall be judged by another, even by</hi> Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. <hi>Honour</hi> (I ſay) <hi>and fear Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is to be your</hi> Iudge; Thoſe who honour me, ſaith God, I will honour; <hi>ſo they who now honour Chriſt, Chriſt will honour at this day; thoſe who now truly fear him, then ſhall not fear him. But as for thoſe, who have now low, mean and contemptible thoughts of Chriſt, Chriſt now knows their thoughts, and I ſhall ſay no more, but they for certain will not be out of his mind at this day, when they ſhall ſtand before his Tribunal-Seat: we alſo hence learn the honour of all true believers, in that they ſtand nearly related to Chriſt: would you not account it an honour to be near related to ſome great</hi> Iudge <hi>on earth; what an honour then is it to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e related, and nearly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to the</hi> Iudge <hi>of the whole world.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>USE II. <hi>Of Comfort and Conſolation,</hi> To all true believers: to all thoſe who have truly own'd, and truly receiv'd, and reſt upon the Lord Ieſus
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97739:7"/>for their Saviour who truly love him and believe on him; it muſt needs go well with all ſuch at this day. This Conſideration takes away all cauſe of fear, terrour and amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in reference to the day of Judgement from all ſuch; and this may be one rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why Chriſt ſhall be the Judge at this day, that hereby thoſe who truly believe on him, might have the greater comfort, in thinking of this day now, and in being at it when it comes. The day of Judgment in it ſelf affords matter of comfort to all ſuch; but much more upon this account. If God himſelf were immediately to be the Judge at this day, true believers would have no cauſe of fear, yet they might be apt to fear. But this conſideration, that Chriſt is to be Iudge at this day, will keep all ſuch from fearing, if it be ſeriouſly thought of. There are ſeveral Conſiderations that might be drawn from the Conſideration of the day of Iudgement, which afford matter of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to the people of God; but this is even the chief and firſt. It will be a great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to believers to fee Chriſt at this day; but a greater comfort that they ſhall be judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by him; and the comfort that is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in this doctrine to all ſuch, will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, if you conſider</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:97739:8"/>1. The Relations between Chriſt and them, they are <hi>the friends of Chriſt,</hi> John 15.15. yea, <hi>the brethren of Chriſt:</hi> Chriſt is call'd <hi>Our elder Brother.</hi> And <hi>Mark</hi> 3.2. <hi>laſt.</hi> Chriſt calls be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers <hi>his Brethren;</hi> yea, they are <hi>the Members of Chriſt;</hi> the Church is the Body of Chriſt, and every true believer a Member in particular, (as the Apoſtle) yea, they are <hi>the Spouſe of Chriſt,</hi> Eph. 5.30. where the Apoſtle alludes to the nearneſs of the Relation between Man and Wife; <hi>Eve</hi> being taken out of <hi>Adam,</hi> and ſo (as he ſpeaks concerning her) <hi>ſhe was fleſh of his fleſh, and bone of his bone:</hi> yea, Chriſt not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtands thus nearly related to all believers, but there is a love in him to them, anſwerable to theſe relations, and above them; now what a comfort is this to have one ſo nearly related to you; (O believers) to have one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o full of love to be your Judge; Surely, it was the love of God to you that appointed Chriſt to be your Judge; If you were to be judg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d by men here on earth, and ſuch a one were to be your Iudge, who (you knew) lov'd you entirely even as his own ſelf, who was your friend, your brother, &amp;c. would not this be a comfort? was not this a comfort (think you) to <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Brethren, that their brother <hi>Joſeph</hi> was Lord of all <hi>Egypt?</hi> would not this have been a comfort enough to <hi>David,</hi> if <hi>Ionathan</hi> his friend had been his Judge? would he have doubted to have found favour?
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97739:8"/>ſuppoſe it could have been, and God ſhould have conſented to it, that thou ſhould'ſt have choſe thy Judge, ſurely thou couldſt not have choſe ſuch another for thy own good and comfort; if thou hadſt choſe the beſt friend thou haſt in the world, ſuppoſe it be thy husband, father, child, or any other, and ſuch a one ſhould have had power to determine how it ſhould have gone with thee for ever, ſurely it ſhould not have gone better, nor ſo well as now it will, nor wouldſt thou have had more comfort and boldneſs in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing before him then now thou wilt. Man may change, Chriſt will not and cannot; man may be deluded and corrupted, Chriſt cannot; yea, let me adde this, ſhould God have told thee, that at this day thou ſhouldſt have been thine own Judge, and it ſhould go with thee to Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity as thou thy ſelf ſhouldſt ſay it ſhould, here would not in this be ſo great a comfort; for its impoſſible that thou ſhouldſt love thy ſelf more, more truly, more fully, yea, ſo much as Chriſt loves thee, being a true believer: were Chriſt to judge himſelf at this day, (if that might be) he would not more certainly free himſelf, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce a ſentence of eternal life then he will to thee, even to thee, whoever thou art, poor, weak, fooliſh, ſinful, if thou doſt truly believe on him: for thou art, (I may ſay himſelf) being a Member of him, and one with him.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, conſider its Jeſus Chriſt who is to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97739:9"/>who hath laid down his life that you might live, who hath bore the wrath of God to free you from it, who hath purchaſed eternal life for you by his blood. Therefore for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain he will, when he ſhall ſit upon his Throne to judge you, look upon you with a loving, ſmiling countenance; ſpeak nothing but words of love, grace and kindneſs to you, and concerning you; therefore for certain he will not pronounce a ſentence of eternal death, but eternal life to you: he ſhould act a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt himſelf, and fruſtrate the end of his coming and dying, of all that he did and ſuffered, if he ſhould not give eternal life to you. Its Ieſus Chriſt who is to be your Iudge, who hath promiſed eternal life to you, <hi>He that believeth on me hath everlaſting life,</hi> Iohn 3. Therefore its againſt his truth and faithfulneſs not to beſtow it upon you at this day, but he being to be the Iudge of the world, it cannot be that he ſhould be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithful and unrighteous, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.4, 5. <hi>Is God unrighteous, God forbid, for how then ſhould God judge the world;</hi> Ics a neceſſary re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite in all Iudges, that they ſhould be righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, much more in the Iudge of the whole world. Its Ieſus Chriſt who is to be your Iudge, who is your Advocate and Interceſſor with God, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever lives to make Interceſſion for you, and plead for you, that you might obtain mercy, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97739:9"/>your ſins, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.1. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when he ſhall come to ſit in Iudgement, he will not doubtleſs, he cannot go againſt his own pleading, notwithſtanding your ſins he will give eternal life to you. Ieſus Chriſt who hath been judg'd for you is to be your Iudge, you need not fear to be judg'd by him. Its that Ieſus Chriſt who is to be your Iudge, to whom your ſins are imputed, who is your Surety, with whoſe righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs you are cloathed, who hath procured the Pardon of all your ſins; and therefore let not this trouble you, to think that your ſins may be ſpoken of, and made known as this day. If it be ſo, it will be by Chriſt who is your righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs himſelf, who hath been made ſin for you, therefore doubt not, notwithſtanding your ſins he will acquit you, and free you from the deſert of them. You will not need any to plead for you, or ſpeak a word for you, nor will you need to ſpeak a word for your ſelf, ſeeing Chriſt himſelf your Advocate is to be your Iudge: O bleſſed believers! you ſhall be judg'd by Chriſt, it is your happineſſe. You are exceedingly in debt to God by your ſins, but Chriſt is to be your Iudge, who is your Surety, who hath paid your debts for you, therefore moſt certainly he will not lay you up in priſon for them, for he hath ſo paid for them, that he requires nothing of you but to beleeve, which you do who are true Chriſtians, to whom I ſpeak, and on whom this
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97739:10"/>doctrine ſmiles and ſpeaks comfort. Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>elf is to be your Iudge, to whom all Power is given for this end, to give you eternal life, <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.2. Chriſt, who hath undertaken and enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to his Father to bring you ſafe to Heaven; Chriſt who is in Heaven now preparing a place for you, and therefore for certain he will carry you to the place he is preparing. Chriſt, from whom you had all your gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e which you have, therefore though but ſmall he will then own it. Chriſt, in whom there is a fulneſs of all grace for you, that you need, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1. and therefore fear not that he will condemn you, becauſe you have no more grace, it being in his hand for you. All the Promiſes of God are made to you in Chriſt, therefore for certain he being to be your Judge, he will make them all good to you. Chriſt who hath prayed for you, that you might be where he is, that you might behold his glory, and partake of it, ſo far as you are capable, <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.22, 24. therefore you need not doubt of going to the place where he is, and receiving of that glory he hath at this day. Its Chriſt who hath help'd you to do all the good that you have done: <hi>Without me ye can do nothing,</hi> John 14.5. <hi>I can do all things through Chriſt who ſtrengthens me,</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) therefore he will own what you have done at this day. You who are believers you have Chriſt in you, <hi>(Chriſt in you the hope of glory)</hi> you have the Spirit of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97739:10"/>Chriſt in you, you are one Spirit with him, (as the Apoſtle ſpeaks.) <hi>you are in Chriſt, Rom.</hi> 8.1. therefore how can it but go well with you at this day, ſeeing Chriſt is to be your Iudge. Ieſus Chriſt, O believers, is to be your Iudge, <hi>who is your Redeemer,</hi> Eph. 1 7. <hi>who hath obtain'd an eternal Redemption for you,</hi> Heb. 9.12. there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for certain you ſhall be perfectly redeemd from all evil at this day, and therefore its cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the day of Redemption to believers, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.30. <hi>Grieve not the holy Spirit whereby you are ſealed to the day of Redemption,</hi> that is, of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, full and compleat Redemption of all thoſe who believe on Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13. <hi>Chriſt hath redeem'd is from the curſe of the Law, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made a curſe for us:</hi> therefore for certain, ſince Chriſt is to pronounce the fentence, <hi>Go ye curſed,</hi> it ſhall not be pronounced to you. Its Chriſt whom you have honoured by believing on him, who will be glorified in you, and admired in you at this day, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10. Therefore for certain you ſhall be honour'd and glorifi'd by him, yea, and therefore you ſhall appear with him in glory, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.3. What cauſe have all true believers to love the appearing of Chriſt, and ſay concerning him, <hi>Come, Lord Jeſus, come quickly,</hi> Rev. 20.4.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:97739:11"/>Theſe words are brought as the Anſwer of the Church to every true believer, whereas all unbelievers ſay in their hearts, and have cauſe to ſay, What come quickly; No, Ieſus; ſtay, ſtay long, ſtay and never come. Surely, none who have any good evidence concerning their faith in Chriſt, can forbear rejoycing, trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phing, wiſhing and praying; deſiring, longing and hoping for this day of Iudgement, becauſe Chriſt is to be the Iudge at this day, if he do but conſider theſe things: But whether belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers do now, as it may be they may not rejoyce in this through the weakneſſe of their faith, and thoſe many doubts and untoward fears that are in him, and wont of meditation and ſerious conſideration concerning theſe things; yet when this day ſhall come, the ſight of Chriſt will fill them with joy and conſolation; it will then, then it will make them to leap and triumph: how glad were the Angels, the Shepherds, old <hi>Simeon</hi> and others at the Birth of Chriſt, at his firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? much more will all true believers be glad and rejoyce at his ſecond coming, though it be to Judgment, yea, therefore becauſe it ſhall be to iudgement. When Chriſt comes to the ſoul in an Ordinance by his Spirit, believers you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>now how welcome he is; had you ever greater joy in your lives? <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.4. what joy! what joy! O what joy! believers, what joy, when Chriſt ſhe I come perſonally at this day, for then
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97739:11"/>Chriſt will come to receive you to himſelf, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.2, 3. Chriſtians, when you think of the day of Iudgement, think of this Scripture, Chriſt will then come to receive you to himſelf, even thee, poor ſoul, who believeſt on him; The firſt coming of Chriſt was great matter of joy: <hi>Abraham ſaw my day,</hi> (that is, by faith) ſaith our Saviour; <hi>my day,</hi> that is, the day of his firſt coming, <hi>and was glad;</hi> we alſo ſhould now by faith look upon the day of this his ſecond come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and be glad: But (as I ſaid before,) if now we are not then we ſhall <hi>Pſal.</hi> 96.10, 11. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 98.4, 5. Thus it will be with all godly men and women, and with all true believers at this day, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19. Now your ſpirits may be ſad and heavy, your ſpirits may ſink and droop; but then, O then, (my Br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>thren and Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in Chriſt,) we ſhall be refreſh'd, we ſhall be cheared and revived, we ſhall have more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort then ever we had ſadneſs, more joy then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver we had ſorrow, more peace then ever we had trouble; our ſpirits ſhall be rais'd Figher in comfort, then ever they were dejected and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt down with fear and grief: we ſhall have as much joy at this day, as believers and wicked men will have ſorrow and terrour; we ſhall be as willing to appear before Chriſt as they will be unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, as ready and forward as they will be back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. When this vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce ſhall found in your ears, <hi>Ariſe, O deal, Chriſt is come to judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:97739:12"/>the Name of Chriſt will make your hearts to leap within you; O bleſſed Ieſus! what Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt on whom <hi>I</hi> have believed, who is the beloved of my ſoul, who hath ſhed his blood for me, is he come to judge me? ſo welcome Jeſus, welcome: I have waited long, long for him; is the time now paſt at an end, is the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter gone, is he now come? with all my heart, moſt gladly let me appear before him; could any and would any hinder you from appearing before him, you would even ſtrive to go to him; you will even be impatient till you have got near him, and never will you think your ſelves too near him. <hi>Henceforth there's laid up for me, &amp;c.</hi> 2 Tim. laſt 8. True believers love the appearing of Chriſt now, how will they love it when it ſhall be: it comforts them now to think of it, much more will it to ſee Chriſt, and well it may, ſeeing then they are to receive a Crown from him. What joy is there when the Bridegroom meets the Bride? what joy is there when Brethren and Friends meet who have been long parted; ſuch (ſuch did I ſay) and a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times more will thy joy be (O believer!) thy joy O now ſad, weeping, ſighing, groaning believer, when thou ſhalt meet Chriſt at Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.34 So I may ſay, <hi>Who is he that ſhall condemn thee at this day</hi> it is Chriſt who is to be thy Iudge; ſurely if the devil (that accuſer of the brethren) or any other, would
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97739:12"/>ſpeak againſt thee, the ſight of Chriſt upon the Tribunal-Seat, will ſilence them all; yea, and thine own conſcience too fully, however now it may trouble thee and accuſe thee, then it will acquit and free thee Chriſt being to be thy Iudge; thy Conſcience will tell thee there's he that died for thee, and loves thee; there's thy life, there's thy hope, thy righteouſneſs, ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication and redemption; thy Friend, thy Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, thy Advocate, thy Surety, thy Saviour; thy Iudge is all theſe to thee. Was not the riſing of the Sun welcom to the <hi>Egyptians</hi> after their long night. So welcom will the riſing of the Sun of Righteouſneſs be to thee at this day. Chriſt who accounts all that is done to thee as done to himſelf, <hi>Saul, Saul, why perſecuteſt thou me? When I was hungry ye fed me &amp;c.</hi> Chriſt who will, and at this day, doth reward thoſe who do thee any good, and puniſh thoſe who do thee any hurt, he ſhall be thy Judge, think then, will he do thee any hurt at this day? what good will he do thee? What good will he not do thee? Chriſt is the beſt friend thou haſt in the world, the beſt thou canſt have. He ſhall be thy Iudge. Beſides all this,</p>
                  <p>Conſider in a word theſe two or three things.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:97739:13"/>1. Chriſt Ieſus is to be thy Iudge, and he is appointed to be thy Iudge by God himſelf; God ſhall judge the world by the Man whom he hath appointed; ſo that what Chriſt ſhall do at this day, God will own and ſtand to; its a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration not without comfort, that God himſelf hath appointed to Chriſt to be our Saviour, that God ſent Chriſt at firſt coming, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ent him to do what he did, and ſuffer what he did, ſo alſo to me its a comfortable conſideration, that God hath appointed Chriſt to be my Iudge, that he will ſend him at his ſecond coming, and ſend him to do what then he ſhall do, and be what then he ſhall be: God, againſt whom thy ſins have been committed, will ſend Chriſt to be thy Iudge, whom he hath ſent to die for thy ſins. It thou hadſt committed treaſon againſt ſome Prince and the Prince himſelf ſhould appoint thy Brother or Friend to be thy Iudge, what wouldſt thou think of this; if Chriſt of himſelf ſhould come to be thy Iudge (if that could be) what were this? thou mightſt fear (though he ſhould judge well concerning thee) his Judgement might not ſtand.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, there will for certain be no change in Chriſt as to his heart and affection to his people at this day; his love and affection will be the ſame to them that it was while here on earth; when he ſuffered for them on the Croſs; Chriſt loves them now in Heaven, as well as he did
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97739:13"/>while here on earth, and ſo he will at this day. So often it is with men, thoſe to whom they were friends, while in a low condition, they ſlight and deſpiſe, and are ſtrange too when they are raiſed; but it is not now, and will not then be ſo with Chriſt; Chriſt was exceeding loving to, and tender over his people while he was here, as he manifeſted many ways, ſo loving, ſo ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der will he be to every one of them at this day; yea ſurely, he will then ſhew much more love to them, then he did while here, in reſpect of his carriage to them; yea, may I not ſay, there will be as much familiarity between them. But</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, conſider when Chriſt ſhall be your Iudge (beloved Chriſtians) it will be as the laſt Iudgement, after which there ſhall be no Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, from which there ſhall be no Appeal; to have the Iudge of an inferiour Court to be your friend were not ſo much, but to have the Iudge of the Chief and Supream Court your inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, entire friend, from which there is no Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal, this were ſomething indeed: The ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence that will paſs from Chriſt at this day, it will be a ſtanding eternal ſentence, that ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo much as be queſtion'd.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, the ſentence of life and happineſs that Chriſt will pronounce to you he himſelf will ſee made good, and make good, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. Chriſt will ſay to the wicked, <hi>Go ye Curſed;</hi> but to his people, <hi>Come ye bleſſed;</hi> what, go to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97739:14"/>either before or after. But come, come with me; Chriſt himſelf will accompany them to Heaven; and therefore in that place before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, <hi>I will come and receive you to my ſelf.</hi> See 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.17. When once Chriſt and believers meet at this day, they will never part, Chriſt will never leave them again, no, not for a moment to eternity; Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ill place eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one in his Manſion about him. Laſtly, Chriſt will be your only Iudge at this day; ſometimes amongſt men there ſits more Judges then one, but Chriſt will be your only Judge, Chriſt will be for you, and there will be none againſt you, and none that you can think or fear may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, becauſe there will be none but Chriſt: Chriſt is our only Saviour, and he will be our only Judge.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="sermon">
               <head>SERMON II.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 3. IS it ſo, &amp;c. Then let all unbelievers, all the enemies of Chriſt think of this, this doctrine looks with a diſmal face upon all ſuch, and ſpeaks dreadful wo and miſery to all ſuch. Its full of ſweetneſs, a breaſt full of conſolation to all true believers, (as you have
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97739:14"/>heard but there's nothing but bitterneſs and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in it to all who ſhall live and die without Chriſt, and enemies to him; and indeed all thoſe who do live without, who will not believe on him, they are enemies to him; <hi>He that is not with us is againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> ſaith Chriſt; he that goes not to Chriſt by faith, is againſt Chriſt, an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to him. Terrour, terrour from this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine to all ſuch. And this is given by ſome as a farther reaſon, why Chriſt ſhall be Iudge at this day, that ſo this day might have the more terrour in it to all ſuch. If God himſelf were immediately to be the Judge, it would not be ſo terrible to wicked men; to have a man who was like themſelves (except ſin) come to judge them, and ſuch a one who was offered again and again to them to be their Saviour, who ſhed his blood, and bore the wrath of God to make way for the ſalvation of ſinners; and this was told them many times, and they were intreated and invited to take Chriſt for their Saviour, and were told (from Chriſt his own mouth) for certain he would not caſt them out, if they would come to him but they ſhould be freed from wrath by him, and at this day receive eternal life from him; but yet they hearing heard not, regarded not, but turn'd their backs upon Chriſt, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed him, made light of him, breaking his Commands, contemning his Ordinances, abuſing his People. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:97739:15"/>To have this Ieſus Chriſt come to judge theſe Rebels againſt him, it muſt needs be terrible, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7. <hi>All Nations ſhall wail becauſe of him;</hi> that is, all unbelievers and enemies to Chriſt in all Nations ſhall wail, not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that then they ſhall be judged, but becauſe then they ſhall be judged by him. This will ſet their Conſciences againſt them in a terrible man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, when this voice ſhall ſound to them, <hi>Ariſe unbelievers, Ariſe wicked men, Jeſus Chriſt is come to judge you;</hi> then Conſcience will tell them, O there's he who was offered to thee to be thy Saviour, but thou didſt refuſe him: there<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s he to whom thou wert often called to come by faith, but thou wouldſt not move in the leaſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him: Now he's come, he's come to judge thee; O what ſhall I do then wilt thou think, is there no believing on him now? Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience will anſwer, No, no; but he is very merciful and compaſſionate, he laid down his life to ſave ſinners, ſurely he will be favourable and gentle to me: No, ſaith Conſcience, he will be the more furious againſt thee, in that then thou wouldſt not accept of him: <hi>Loe, he is now come in flaming! alas, alas, woe, woe, he is now come in flaming fire to render vengeaence upon thee,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.7, 8. There is not the leaſt ſpark of love, mercy and compaſſion to be found in him now towards thee, nothing but fire, nothing but wrath againſt thee. Think not you
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97739:15"/>who are ungodly ſinners; you who are unbeliev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers think not, it will fare ever the better with you at this day, becauſe Chriſt ſhall be your Iudge: No ſurely, it will be worſe for you, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept you now turn, repent and believe. Think not, that becauſe Chriſt was ſo meek and loving while here on earth, that he will be ſo to you at this day; yea, Chriſt was angry with wicked men while here upon earth, <hi>Mark</hi> 3.5. much more will be angry with them when he ſhall be their Judge, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.16. Wicked men will not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure ſo much as to look Chriſt in the face, <hi>Hide us from the face of him that ſitteth upon the Throne,</hi> (then which nothing will be more love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, amiable, refreſhing and deſireable to believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers) <hi>and from the wrath of the Lamb, for the great day of his wrath is come, and who ſhall be able to ſtand?</hi> The wrath of the Lamb, where (by joyning wrath and Lamb together) this thought ſeems to be anſwered, Chriſt was as a Lamb while here on earth, meek and patient, therefore ſurely he will not be ſevere at this day: yes, but he will; he will be full of wrath againſt wicked men. The day of his wrath: the day of Chriſt his firſt coming was a day of love and mercy, but the day of his ſecond come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will be a day of wrath to all ungodly ones; and ſuch wrath that they ſhall not be able to ſtand at this day, <hi>Who ſhall be able to ſtand?</hi> ſtand they ſhall, but it will be intolerable to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97739:16"/>them to ſtand, and ſore againſt their wills? Chriſt was as a Lamb at his firſt coming but to wicked men he will at his ſecond coming be as a Lion, as he is called, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5 5. <hi>Pſal</hi> 2.12. When his wrath is kindled but a little, how then will it fare with wicked men when his wrath ſhall be kindled to the utmoſt. O unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, who am I ſpeaking to, not to the walls, but to you? The Lord Ieſus Chriſt who is to be the Iudge of the world now calls upon you to come to him; Come unto me, come off from your ways of ſin, own me, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke hold of me by faith; if you ſhall not bear and obey, his voice will be quite contrary to you at this day, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part ye curſed, &amp;c.</hi> Mat. 25.41. I would have freed you from the curſe of the Law if you would have believed on me, but you would not, now therefore you ſhall ſuffer it; And ſo, I Ieſus Chriſt, who offered to free you from it, pronounce it againſt you, and in flict it upon you, <hi>Depart ye curſed;</hi> ſo Mat. 7.23. Then, that is, at the day of Iudgement, <hi>I will profeſs I never knew you, &amp;c.</hi> This will be the voice of Chriſt to every of you who hear me this day (and all other whoever) who live in ſin and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief; depart, but whither, not into the world again; O that would be a pleaſing word to ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners if it ſhould be ſo, no, but <hi>Depart into ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting fire;</hi> Depart, whither? into Hell, where
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97739:16"/>there is no hing, but torment; and exquiſite tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as bad, yea, worſe; worſe, yea, incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceivably worſe then fire: VVo is us, will ſinners then think, and wel may they think. But how long muſt we be there? how long? a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years, a thouſand years; wo, wo is us indeed, what ſo long? In fire ſo long? yea, for ever, ever, ever, depart into everlaſting fire. O how will this word fill the hearts of wicked men. Your hearts, O wicked men, (as many of you as are here) if you continue ſuch, thy heart O drunkard; thy heart, O prophaner of the Sabbath; thy heart, O covetous wretch, &amp;c. with the hearts of all other wicked men; how I ſay will this voice fill ſuch mens hearts with horrour and amazement. O heart-aking, trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling word<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when Iudges amongſt men do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce a ſentence of death upon Malefactors, would not this make thy heart ake within, and make thee even tremble every joynt of thee: if for ſome crime ſuch a ſentence ſhould be paſt upon thee by a Iudge on Earth; Depart to be hanged, drawn and quartered, to be burnt, &amp;c. what an aſtoniſhing word will this be to thee, when Chriſt ſhall ſay, Depart, &amp;c. but what ſhall my company be, may wicked men think: Chriſt tells them, the devil and his Angels: but how long will it be ere this fire be kindled, till this be fulfilled?
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:97739:17"/>will there be not ſome time of reſpite before we ſhall go into the fire, ſeeing we muſt never come out; no, it will be ready prepared and kindled, <hi>Depart into everlaſting Fire prepared, &amp;c.</hi> Pray confider, it appears by the ſentence, Jeſus Chriſt will not be milde and merciful to wicked men at this day, for theſe are the words of Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the Judge, he tells you he will ſay thus to wicked men at this day. The People of God (as I told you) could not poſſibly have a Judge, whoſe Preſence would be more delightful; wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men could not poſſibly have a Judge, whoſe Preſence, would, could be more terrible, more dreadful. Were the worſt enemy thou haſt (O unbeliever) to be thy Judge, yea, let me ſay, were the devil himſelf to be thy Iudge; it would not be ſo dreadful as to have that Lamb Ieſus Chriſt thy Iudge. O unbelievers, the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſhall be your Iudge, who knows what is in you, who knows your hearts and very thoughts, <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.3, <hi>laſt.</hi> Chriſt did while here on earth, and therefore be ſure he will at this day; there will be no deluding and deceiving Chriſt, my friends, who is to be your Iudge. Ieſus Chriſt ſhall be your Iudge, who is and ever was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly holy, yea, as God, infinitely holy, more holy then the Angels; it cannot therefore go well with ſinners, that love ſin and live in ſin; That little holineſs that is in Gods people here, makes them even to hate wicked men (as ſuch)
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:97739:17"/>and that with a perfect hatred, and doth and will Chriſt love them? Chriſt is to be your Judge, who is an entire Lover of his Father and his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers glory; now the ſins of wicked men they are committed againſt God, and he is greatly diſhonoured, and ſo injured by them, therefore he will undoubtedly be furious againſt wicked men at this day? How angry was <hi>Moſes</hi> (from that love to God which he had) with thoſe who cauſ'd <hi>Aaron</hi> to make the golden Calf, though he were the me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>keſt man that ever was; yet they bad diſhonoured God, and <hi>Moſes</hi> he is greatly wrath; <hi>He breaks the Tables, &amp;e.</hi> Exod. 30. If <hi>Moſes</hi> that meek man were ſo angry with the people for that one ſin, how angry will Chriſt be (notwithſtanding his meekneſs,) when he ſhall come to puniſh wicked men for all their ſins; Chriſt ſhall be your Iudge, O wicked men, who then ſhall be your Advocate, who ſhall ſtand up to plead for you? O that <hi>I</hi> could but fully make known to you what will be your miſery at this day, and that upon this Account, becauſe Chriſt ſhall be your Iudge; but truly I perceive it more then I can expreſs it to you. Sure I am, the ſight of Chriſt upon the Throne, will be the dreadfulleſt ſight to them that ever they ſaw: It will be dreadful to them to ſee all the world on fire about them, but more dreadful will the ſight of Chriſt be to them. It muſt needs be that Chriſt ſhould look
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:97739:18"/>upon, and ſpeak in a terrible manner to all ſuch, when he ſhall be their Iudge. O wicked men, ſin cauſed me to ſweat drops of Hood, it pierc'd me, crucified me, and put me into inconceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able torment in bearing the wrath of God; and yet, (though you heard of this, you loved ſin and took delight in it; it was your meat and drink, a pleaſure to you. All that ever you had you had for my ſake; you had never liv'd ſo long, never been out of hell ſo long, never had had one houre of comfort, eaſe, reſt and peace, never the leaſt good but for me; and yet I could have no love from you; and yet you regarded me not at all; I required of you but to receive me, but to believe on me that you might be ſav'd by me, and yet that you would not, yea, and did not ſo much as in truch ſeek, deſire, and endeavour it. Of all things you thought leaſt of me, cared leaſt for me, yea, even nothing for me; you carried it to me as if I had been worth nothing; you did even what lay in you to fruſtrate the end of my coming into the world and dying; had all carried it to me as you did I had been no Saviour. O unbelieving ſinners, you have been deſperate enemies to me; think not now that you ſhall have the leaſt friendſhip from me; ſpeak not a word to me, I will not hear you. I'le now make you to know what it was to deſpiſe ſuch a loving; ſuffering crucified Saviour; I your Iudge am your enemy, I will
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:97739:18"/>now ſend you to a place where you ſhall never ſee, never hear of me and mercy any more, to a place where you ſhall be ever learning by your ſufferings: how great my ſufferings was which you deſpiſed, and what your ſin was to make light of ſuch a Saviour: I can't now ſave you, I will not now ſave you: yea, I Jeſus Chriſt the Saviour of the world condemn you to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſs Pit: <hi>I who have the Keys of Hell, and of Death,</hi> Rev. 1.17. open Hell to you, and inflict eternal Death upon you: had you cloſ'd with me, and own'd me, none ſhould have hurt you; but now there's none that can, that will, that ſhall help you: lean ſtill upon your works, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and good meanings, and whatever elſe you lean'd upon, and made a Saviour of before, lean ſtill upon it, and ſee if it can keep you from that place whither I ſhall ſend you. O un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believing ſinner! I could and would have ſav'd thee once to the utmoſt, but now I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy thee to the utmoſt. I had a Commiſſion and full power to make thee happy if thou wouldſt; I have now Commiſſion and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to make thee miſerable for ever. I told thee I would certainly ſave thee notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding thy ſins if thou wouldſt come to me; <hi>I</hi> was very real and hearty in it, <hi>I</hi> would now have been as good as my word, thou ſhouldſt now have found the truth of it, but thou didſt queſtion it, and wouldſt not believe me
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:97739:19"/>but thoughtſt thy ſelf too great a ſinner for me to ſave, (as it is with ſome) I now tell thee, thou ſhalt into everlaſting fire; and I am as real in this as I was in that, and in that as I am in this; queſtion the truth of this if thou wilt, thy ſenſe ſhall tell thee preſently, that I really mean as I ſay Yea, I told thee this before, in my Word, and by my Miniſters, that I would at this day ſend thee into everlaſting fire, if thou wouldſt not believe on me; but thou wert not affected or moved by this word, and didſt not believe it; the day I told thee of thou ſeeſt is come, the ſentence I told thee I would pronounce, thy ears ſhall now hear, I now pronounce it againſt thee; ſuch as ye will or may be, the words of Chriſt to thee, even to thee, to thee (I ſay) if thou doſt not come in, leave thy ſin and cloſe with him; yea, more terrible, believe it, will his words be to thee for the matter, then I can ſpeak and tell thee; and for the meaſure of them, what ſhall be wanting in the words of Chriſt to thee, thy conſcience will make up, and be making up in thee to Eternity? VVill it not be dreadful, think you, at this day for <hi>Judas</hi> who betrayed Chriſt, for thoſe who came to take him (of whom we reade ſome went backward and fell on the ground) how fraid and amazed will all thoſe be at this day, when they ſhall ſtand before Chriſt his Tribunal, all thoſe who had any hand in putting him to death, to whom God gave
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:97739:19"/>not repentance; all thoſe who ſpet upon him, and mocked him, and ſmote him, and cried out. <hi>Cruciſie him;</hi> will it not be dreadful to them, think you, when they ſhall ſee that ſame Ieſus, whom they ſo dealt with, ſitting as their Judge: doubtleſs you will ſay yes; why, ſurely, my friends, it will be little leſs dreadful to every one of you, who hearing of Chriſt yet refuſe him, and continue in your ſins knowingly and wilfully under the light of the Goſpel; cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, as there never was ſuch love and mercy heard of, as Chriſt hath ſhewn to the ſinful ſons of men in his ſuffering, ſo never was there ſuch fury, ſuch wrath and indignation as Chriſt will ſhew at this day, againſt all ungodly men and unbelievers. Its not ſaid. Chriſt will come in fire, taking vengeance on thoſe who crucified him, but on thoſe who know not God, and obey not the Goſpel of his Son; yea, certainly it will even go worſe at this time with you who now live under the ſound of the Goſpel, and yet continue in ſin and unbelief then it will (a leaſt) with ſome of them who crucified Chriſt, for they did it ignorantly as Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Father forgave them, for they know not what they do;</hi> but you will not be able to plead ignorance; you know you ſhould be ſober and conſtant in duty, &amp;c. That you ſhould beleeve on Chriſt, and yet you do not, you will not.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 4. <hi>Exhort.</hi> 2. To move you to ſeek out
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:97739:20"/>for an intereſt in Chriſt; neither is it an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument that is empty and light, that hath little in it. Both the comings of Chriſt are ſtrong Arguments to move ſinners to come in and cloſe with him; Chriſt came into the world to ſave ſinners, O therefore, to Chriſt, my friends; cloſe with him. Chriſt will come again to judge ſinners, O therefore alſo to Chriſt ſinners, to Chriſt; take hold of him, own him in truth for thy Saviour, which if you ſhall the Uſe of Conſolation from this doctrine belongs to you, if not, the other uſe of terrour is thy portion, believe it, ſinner. Men and Brethren, when you are called upon to believe on Chriſt, it is indeed to believe on One who hath been in the world, and now is gone out of it, whom thou ſeeſt not and canſt not now ſee, he being in Heaven, in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and far above thee; but remember, think of it, it is yet to believe on one who will come again, whom though yet thou haſt not ſeen, thou ſhalt ſee. VVhen you are called upon to believe on Chriſt, you may think, who is Chriſt, where is Chriſt, we ſee him not, we never ſaw him, he is gone out of the world: <hi>I</hi> but he will, he certainly will come again, and that to judge thee, and then thou ſhalt ſee him: Hadſt thou no need of Chriſt to be thy Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, (as ſome poſſibly may think they have but little need) yet ſeeing Chriſt ſhall be thy Judge, it concerns thee to cloſe with him. Its a high
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:97739:20"/>offence, yea, and an injury to Jeſus Chriſt, not to believe on him, yea, the greateſt offence and injury that can be offered to him, yea, that ever was offered to him: its worſe then to crucifie Chriſt; many of thoſe who crucified Chriſt will be ſav'd by him at this day, ſo many as did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve on him, as ſeveral of them did, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. <hi>Peter</hi> tells them they had crucified the Lord of Life, and they being prickt at the heart, cry out, <hi>Men and brethren-what ſhall we do? Peter</hi> tells them, <hi>They muſt beleeve on Chriſt, and</hi> 3000 <hi>of them were added to the Chrich:</hi> ſo that to believe on Chriſt, is more pleaſing to God and Chriſt then crucifying of Chriſt was diſpleaſing, and therefore nor to believe on Chriſt crucified is worſe and more diſpleaſing then to crucifie him: now pray tell me, VVill it be, do you think, for your advantage at this day, ſo to have diſpleas'd and injur'd Chriſt your Judge? Doubtleſs this was one end why this truth was diſcovered to us, that Jeſus Chriſt ſhall come again and be the Judge of the world, that it might be a motive to ſtir us up to believe on him. VVere you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to have any thing to do with Chriſt nor Chriſt with you, you might ſtill reject and diſpraiſe him, it would not be ſuch folly. But Jeſus Chriſt is to be your Iudge, O therefore give ear, open your hearts to the Voice of God and Chriſt in his VVord, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling upon you to come to Chriſt &amp; believe on him,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:97739:21"/>Chriſt tells you, <hi>If you beleeve not, you are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned already,</hi> John 3 Certainly therefore he will condemn you at this day if you do not: Chriſt tells you again, <hi>v. laſt, that he who believes not on him ſhall not ſee life, but the wrath of God abideth on him;</hi> therefore you may aſſuredly know, that if you die in unbelief he will not give you life, but pour forth that wrath of God upon you, <hi>Mark laſt</hi> 16. <hi>He that believes not,</hi> (ſaith Chriſt <hi>ſhall be damned;</hi> Chriſt ſpeaks plain, Remember it is the Word of Chriſt who is to be your Iudge; who therefore, he having ſaid, <hi>that if you beleeve not you ſhall be damn'd,</hi> will, without any hope to the contrary, not only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn but damn you too at this day, if you ſhall not believe on him. Certainly, there's none of you but muſt needs be convinc'd from this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine (had there never been any thing elſe before ſaid to you about believing) that its beſt for you to believe on Chriſt, ſeeing its that he requires and deſires of you; neither certainly could you hear this truth, but you would ſeek after faith, and be greatly troubled if you do not believe, if you were not deluded and deceived. Now many are the deluſions and deceits whereby men are kept from being mov'd by this and ſuch like truths; amongſt the reſt this is even the chief and moſt common; though men do not believe, yet they pleaſe themſelves with a groundleſs hope that they do, <hi>I</hi> ſhall therefore put you in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:97739:21"/>mind of one place of Scripture, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17. My friends, Chriſt is to be your Iudge, you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny it; the Word of God abundantly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms it; now will he give eternal life to you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept you believe on him? he profeſſeth that he will not once and again, and you certainly can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not think that he will; well then, do you believe on him? you'll ſay (its lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>) yes, you do, or you hope you do as well a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> any other: Hear now the VVord of God, <hi>If thou doſt believe on Chriſt thou art a new creature, &amp;c.</hi> VVhat ſayſt thou, Is it ſo? haſt thou left thy old ſins? art thou not the ſame man as ever thou wert? haſt thou not as hard a heart, as blinde an under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding? doſt thou not live as bad, or it may be a worſe life then formerly thou didſt? art thou not as prophane, as vain, as worldly as ever? Or if thou haſt amended ſome things, yet do not ſome old things remain ſtill? doſt thou not live in ſome of thy old luſts, and that with as much love to them, delight in them, and as little trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for them as ever; is it thus with thee? Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, are all things become new with thee, are thy affections new affections, thy deſires new de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, thy love a new love, thy fear a new fear, thy delights new delights? doſt thou deſire grace in ſtead of the world, love God in ſtead of ſelf &amp; the world, fear ſin in ſtead of outward evils and God in ſtead of men? doſt thou delight in duty, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and God, in ſtead of ſin, vanity and the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:97739:22"/>world? is thy company alſo new? are thy thoughts, thy words and diſcourſe new? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is it not thus with thee? Then if the VVord of God be true, (and deny it if thou durſt) thou art not in Chriſt, that is, thou doſt not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elieve on him; pleaſe thy ſelf, (if thou thinkeſt good) with thy falſe hope, that thou doſt believe: but know that Chriſt will try thee by this Scripture, (with ſuch like) and judge of thy faith ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to it, and of thee according to thy faith, and then thou wilt ſee thy folly, and for certain be turn'd into the place of unbeliev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, which place if thou wouldſt know. See <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8.</p>
               <p>Secondly, is it ſo that Chriſt is to be your Judge, then he exhorted to yield obedience to the Commands of Chriſt; when you hear or reade any of the Commands of Chriſt, remember this, they are the Commands of him who is to be thy Judge: would you know what the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of Chriſt are? I anſwer, all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of God are the Commands of Chriſt: the ten Commands are the Commands of Chriſt: but more particularly and eſpecially you may reade what the Commands of Chriſt are, in the fifth, ſixth and ſeventh chapters of <hi>Matthew,</hi> beſid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s other places: Chriſt commands you <hi>to love your enemies, to pray, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> up for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſelves treaſure in Heaven, to ſeck firſt the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God and his Righteouſneſs; to do as you
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:97739:22"/>would be done by &amp;c.</hi> theſe with the reſt of the Commands of Chriſt ye ſhould obey, yea, muſt obey if ever it go well with you, when Chriſt ſhall come to judge you: if you ſhall refuſe to obey them, you may reade what will be your doom at this day, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.27. <hi>Thoſe mine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies that would not that I ſhould reign ever them, bring them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ither and ſlay them before me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, beware how you make uſe of his Ordinances, Preaching the Goſpel, the Lords Supper, &amp;c. <hi>Take heed how you hear,</hi> (ſaith Chriſt,) the ſame I may ſay concerning every Ordinance of Chriſt, take heed how you receive the Lords Supper, take heed how you pray, how you make uſe of Baptiſin, &amp;c. Look to it that it be according to his inſtitution, and as he requires; if you uſe the Ordinances that he hath appointed in any way and manner but what he hath appointed, moſt certainly to your coſt you will hear of it at this day, however you may now make light of it, and plead for that which is either directly contrary to his inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or no way (at leaſt) according to it. People ſhould take he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d how they make uſe of the Ordinances of Chriſt, and Miniſters alſo how they adminiſter them, becauſe they are the Ordinances and Inſtitutions of Chriſt, who is to be the Judge of us all.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, hence be exhorted to beware how you carry to the friends of Chriſt, and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt, as you love your ſelves, and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:97739:23"/>deſire Chriſt his good, will at this day carry it well to them, for as you carry to them, ſo Chriſt accounts you carry it to himſelf, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. <hi>lat. In as much as you did it not to one of theſe, you did it not to me:</hi> and for the Miniſters of Chriſt. <hi>Mat</hi> 10.40. <hi>He that receiveth you receineth me, &amp;c.</hi> VVo be to thoſe which deſpiſe and injure the friends and ſervants of Chriſt, ſeeing Chriſt is to be their Judge. VVhich conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration alſo may encourage the Miniſters of the Goſpel, and all true believers, to undergo with patience all the hard uſage and ſpeeches of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men againſt them for their faithfulneſs to Chriſt, his ways and truth; certainly, in that Chriſt is to be their Judge they ſhall not loſe their reward, as thoſe neither ſhall not who ſhew them kindneſs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>s</hi> He that receives a Prophet, (ſaith Chriſt the Judge of the world, who is to reward every man according to their works) <hi>in the name of a Prophet ſhall receive a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets reward, and he that receives a righ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eous man in the name of a righteous man, ſhall receive a righteous mans reward.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, hence be exhorted to beware how you take upon you the Name of Chriſt, and how you make uſe of his Name. 1 Beware how you take upon you the Name of Chriſt, that is, that you do not account and call your ſelves Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and yet live in ſin, as it is with many? what will Chriſt ſay to ſuch when he ſhall come to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:97739:23"/>judge them; O thou wicked perſon, thou drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard, was I ever ſuch a one, did I ever ſo, thou vain, prophane, covetous, idle, railing perſon, &amp;c? Did I ever live after that manner? was not I holy, did I not in all things conſtantly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey the Commands of God? how then durſt thou to bear my Name upon thee, and call thy ſelf a Chriſtian, as if I had liv'd as thou didſt? for truly that's <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ven imply'd, when a wicked man calls himſelf a Chriſtian, a diſciple of Chriſt, what doth he but even ſay, that Chriſt was ſuch a one as he is, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. <hi>Let eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one that nameth the Name of Chriſt depart from iniquity;</hi> let very one who calls himſelf a Chriſtian, and wouldſt be called and accounted ſo by others, endeavour to live as Chriſt did, or wo be to him alſo ſeeing Chriſt is to be his Iudge; its even as great a diſhonour and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace as you can caſt upon Chriſt, to call your ſelves by his Name, and yet live in the devils ways. Secondly, beware how you make uſe of the Name of Chriſt, and that either in ſpeaking to God or to men; when you ſpeak of him one to another, ſpeak not of him as of other men, peak awfully and reverentially of him, and that in a proper diſcourſe, not upon every vain and trifling occaſion: there is a taking the Name of Chriſt in vain, as well as the taking of the Name of God in vain; and as God ſaith, <hi>God will not hold him guiltleſs who taketh his Name</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:97739:24"/>in vain; ſo when you uſe the Name of Chriſt to God in Prayer, look to it that it be with faith on his Name, and that it be from a true love and reſpect to him; uſe not his Name as a meer cuſtomary thing (as its to be feared i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s with the moſt: Its the cuſtom to ſay for Chriſt his ſake, in and through Chriſt &amp;c. and therefore they ſay, as when they ask any mercy of God, and when they bleſs him for any mercy. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber this, no unbeliever can uſe the Name of Chriſt aright as he ought to do: Chriſt is to be your Iudge, certainly it will not go well on thy ſide at that great day, if this ſhall ſtand upon Record, and be brought forth againſt you; Thou didſt often uſe the Name of Chriſt, but thou hadſt no love to him, no faith on him, but after a vain and looſe manner, as if he had bin a meer fancie; or but a mean perſon, or one of whom thou ſtoodſt in no great need, and hadſt no cauſe to fear and honour.</p>
               <p>To the right making uſe of the Name of Chriſt in Prayer to God, it is required as that you ſhould have love to him, and faith on him, ſo that you ſhould be deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſenſible of your own vileneſs, and total abſolute unworthineſs to receive any thing from God immediately; that you ſhould indeed deſire, expect and hope for all that you a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k of God in his Name, for his ſake and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:97739:24"/>not in the leaſt for your own ſake, or the ſake of what you have, or have done, or for the ſake of your Prayers: yea, or for Gods ſake; that is, for his mercy ſake, and his faithful ſake in the Promiſe, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to Chriſt; every time you ask any thing in Chriſt and do not ſo ask it, you take the Name of Chriſt in vain; its high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpleaſing both to God and Chriſt: And beſid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, heres alſo this in it, That you will for certain go without whatſoever you ſo ask, though you ask never ſo often and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo long, ſo (without repentance and pardon) you are like to ſuffer for it when Chriſt ſhall come to judge; There's many a man who prays much but receives no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, becauſe he asks not in the Name of Chriſt: and there is many a one who doth ask in the Name of Chriſt verbally, in words; yet not asking in his Name cordially, from his heart, and in a right man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, with faith on his Name, and love to him, and a deep ſeaſe of his unworthineſs to receive any thing but through him, ſo as to deſire, hope and expect it, only for his ſake, he goes without what he asks, and not only ſo, but pulls down judgments from God in ſtead of mercies, and makes his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition far worſe, and himſelf a ſubject fitter for wrath when Chriſt ſhall come to judge him.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:97739:25"/>the ſame may be ſaid of praiſing for any mercy that we receive: VVe ought not only to praiſe God for mercy, but to praiſe for it in Chriſt; and that ſo, as really to account the mercy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, to have come from God only for Chriſt his ſake, that is, from grace in Chriſt, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>
               <hi>Bridge</hi>'s <hi>Remains,</hi> being Eight Sermons, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>1 <hi>Of Mans Bleſſedneſs.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Affections rightly Placed.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>How to walk with God in our Calling?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4 <hi>Of good and bad Company.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. <hi>The Carnality of Profeſſors.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6. <hi>What our Work is, and how to be done?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>7. <hi>Soul-Reſignation into the Hands of God.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>8. <hi>The Dignity and Duty of Gods called ones.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>A Diſcourſe of Chriſts coming.</hi> By <hi>Theoph. Gale.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Nature and Principles of Love, as the End of the Commandment,</hi> declared in ſome of the laſt Sermons of Mr. <hi>Joſeph Caryl,</hi> with an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle of <hi>John Owen</hi> D.D.</p>
            <p>All ſold by <hi>John Hancock Sen. &amp; Jun.</hi> at the three Bibles in <hi>Cornhill.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:97739:25"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
